<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Generated by Site-Server v6.0.0-387645565d41b7a620647e881491b6238629efca-1 (http://www.squarespace.com) on Wed, 03 Jul 2024 21:35:21 GMT
--><rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:media="http://www.rssboard.org/media-rss" version="2.0"><channel><title>little left over</title><link>https://littleleftover.com/</link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 18:04:16 +0000</lastBuildDate><language>en-US</language><generator>Site-Server v6.0.0-387645565d41b7a620647e881491b6238629efca-1 (http://www.squarespace.com)</generator><description><![CDATA[]]></description><item><title>skilful</title><category>restaurants</category><dc:creator>Jamie Rumbelow</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2019 17:04:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://littleleftover.com/blog/2019/12/31/skilfully</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d:5a945a09652dea5235cfb463:5e0b8da0192cf25f69200792</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>There’s a wonderful passage in Fuschia Dunlop’s <em>Shark’s Fin and Szechuan Pepper</em>, a book full of wonderful passages, somewhere close to the end:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Many Chinese friends have spoken to me over the last few years of a historical progression from ‘eating to fill your belly’ (<em>chi bao</em>), through ‘eating plenty of rich food’ (<em>chi hao</em>), to ‘eating skilfully’ (<em>chi qiao</em>).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>She’s describing the shifting relationship with food as China has developed and modernised: millennia of relative scarcity, yielding to ‘the thrill of plenty’, and finally, recently, a more discerning class of gourmets. It’s about the Chinese writ large – not as some exceptionless rule, of course, but a general trend – and, in Dunlop’s memoirs, is part of the pivot to the moment of redemption, when her gaudy, ethically questionable excess gives way to an altogether more thoughtful, discerning approach.</p>
<p>It’s a great book, her cookbooks are even better, and I’ll review them all here in more detail some time soon. But, for now, I’d like to ponder this transition as it applies to individuals.</p>
<hr>
<p>As I walked to Osteria Francescana, I felt nervous. I felt nervous because my expectations were high – higher than I think they’ve ever been. What if it wasn’t worth the price? What if, after spending more more on one meal than I do on my rent, my experience was mediocre, my response lukewarm. What would I <em>say</em> to people? How could I justify it? It always made sense before, even when I knew I couldn’t really afford it. This is what I <em>do</em>. This is what I care about. I’ve never felt nervous before. But I did this time.</p>
<p>The restaurants that I really love, those I go back to time and again for purely gastronomic reasons, are not really comparable with Osteria Francescana, because they’re doing completely different things. Even when you compare it to other restaurants doing the same thing, the comparators are unclear.</p>
<p>When you get to the level that Bottura and team are competing at, I’m not entirely sure there is a meaningful standard at all against which you can judge them. The meal might not be what you wanted, or expected, or might not be what you’d be willing to pay anywhere else, but that’s not really the point. You’re going for the experience, broadly construed, and you’re going for the brand name. You’re going to say you’ve been, but you’re also going just to go. You see?</p>
<p>Let me try to put it another way. On every tasting menu, the meal is allowed to be hit-and-miss, because <a href="https://littleleftover.com/blog/2017/11/24/little-things">the chef isn’t cooking for you</a>. She’s cooking for herself, and you go to get a glimpse of what she’s thinking about and trying to express; if you enjoy the food, it’s a bonus, rather than the point.</p>
<p>But that’s also an easy way to sidestep and ignore real problems, cover for an experience that should be, in its totality, pretty fucking spectacular, <em>thank-you-very-much</em>. Was Francescana pretty fucking spectacular? Honestly? No, not really.</p>
<p>It was technically impressive, for sure. After a couple of amuses bouche, we were served ‘Pollution Revolution’, a light clam consommé, salty and rich in umami, sat atop a wild sea herb sludge, thick and green. It was evocative and tasty, beautifully served in an oyster shell. Spaghettini was next, a deeply fishy, buttery, sea urchin broth, over raw Hokkaido scallop. Fish courses were carefully cooked and wines thoughtfully paired.</p>
<p>It was conceptually clever. When I asked him about Alinea and how he would compare his food to Achatz’s, Bottura told me that "we're doing different things; he does theatre, my food is more conceptual". And he was right: there was some incredibly clever moves. ‘When north meets south’ was a southern pizza made from northern ingredients: burnt polenta chips, a mozzarella risotto and a rich tomato passata; it looked nothing and tasted everything like a slice of Neapolitan Margherita. ‘Pasta al pesto in abstract’ was a good facsimile of penne al peso, pesto soup pock-marked by little chunks of semolina (or was it potato? I honestly can’t remember.) The much-lauded ‘Five Ages of Parmigiano Reggiano’ was a little underwhelming, but that may be because I cook with parmesan most days and use it as a substitute for salt; I’m a saturated in it, and could have lost the subtleties as a result.</p>
<p>But in spite of all of the technical achievement, conceptual cleverness, creative whimsy, I found myself almost forcing myself to enjoy it. The room was bare, cool, table lit by a harsh overhanging lamp. Entering the restaurant, ringing the doorbell and waiting for entrance, didn’t add an exclusive allure but rather inconvenience and a disorienting lack of charm. A huge Damien Hirst (Bottura proudly proclaiming a part of his own personal collection) hung in my periphery. I wasn’t comfortable.</p>
<p>And there were dishes that, in retrospect, I just didn’t like very much. ‘Wagyu non wagyu’ would have been better named ‘Pork and chewy lardo’. ‘The crunchy part of the lasagna’, added as a surprise course, was underwhelming. Visually beautiful, the cracker stained with the colours of the Repubblicà, but served with a paltry spoonful of under-seasoned ragù and a béchamel which had already sodden the crunch out of the cracker before it had even arrived at our table.</p>
<p>None of it was bad — I’d bloody hope not, too — but with the label ‘best restaurant in the world’ hanging over the whole experience, it didn’t represent an order of magnitude better food than that at, say, Bright, or Le Servan (neither of which have one Michelin star, let alone three.) Of course it’s apples and oranges; I don’t want to compare them. But you can’t help it. And, when dealing with restaurants so <em>important</em>, high on lists that make a claim to objectivity, you definitely should.</p>
<hr>
<p>Do you remember the first time? I’ve been eating quite seriously for quite a few years, and my first proper tasting menu (Midsummer House, December 2015) was a revelation. All of a sudden, this wasn’t food-as-convenience, Café Rouge, hurried to table with a surly sigh. This was <em>flavour</em>, and artistry. It was the sort of food that made me laugh and cheer and blush at the price tag. It was a wine pairing – my first Au Bon Climat – and hospitality that felt like an unrivalled joy, not a surly sigh in sight.</p>
<p>But now I’m eating at really excellent restaurants a lot of the time, and tasting menus feel overwrought, especially against a backdrop of plates at P Franco, bowls of nouilles dan dan at Trois Fois Plus de Piment and the steak tartare at CAM. Bottles of light, fun, low-intervention wines drunk at my pace; glorious, simple food to slurp and munch and spill without scruples. No tweezers. Ugly delicious.</p>
<p>It’s becoming more tiring to eat skilfully, if eating skilfully demands so much of you, as Osteria Francescana did. There is food prepared with just as much love, attention, skill found in dozens of bistros and bars in Paris and London. I’ve regressed, in short, back down to eating plenty of rich food, on my time, in my terms.</p>
<p>I don’t know if the regression will continue (I doubt it). But I’m glad it’s happened. I’m happier now. My heart feels fuller, and I feel more connected to what I’m eating. It’s not abstract beauty anymore. It doesn’t need to be conceptual in order to impress me. It just needs to be delicious. Now that I’ve done the Michelin / tasting menu thing, I’m happier when it’s simpler. Deliciousness should be the goal, not cleverness.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d/1577815612790-59MU9L9IHD5XM8797VUH/68873343_244150896543855_4198454877796204485_n.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1080" height="1080"><media:title type="plain">skilful</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>love letters</title><category>restaurants</category><category>france</category><dc:creator>Jamie Rumbelow</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 19:57:04 +0000</pubDate><link>https://littleleftover.com/blog/2019/1/31/love-letters</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d:5a945a09652dea5235cfb463:5c5352a3e79c704bd3ed47a6</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>I love Bill Buford’s <em>Heat</em>, because if you strip back the intrigue and drama – the kitchen confidentiality – the long, almost academic passages on the history of the tortellino, the little <em>Babbo</em> vignettes (not so <em>molto</em> now, but worth preserving for posterity’s sake) you see that the book is not really a book about food at all. It’s a love letter.</p>
<p>That sort of love – deep, foundational, structural, personal, the sort of love you only really find in a love letter, or maybe a Richard Curtis movie – is what I look for in good writing. Knowledge is important, sure. Insight perhaps more so. Humour, honesty, urgency. But I place a premium on the sincerity of a writer’s love for her subject, because criticism needs to come from a desire to improve, not a desire to condemn. Buford could have easily written a tell-all romp through the underbelly of the New York dining scene, or sworn his way on TV through a series of grubby kitchens (and grubbier chefs), or shat out yet another book on hygge, and probably would have found a wider audience. But he didn’t. He writes excellently, in fluid, elegant prose, about a subject which he <em>wants</em> you to love as much as he does. It’s a love letter to Italy. And he pushes you to think deeply about the place, and about its food, and about the food you eat, and about yourself, and about the relationship between all of the above. It’s a truly excellent book.</p>
<p>The trouble, of course, is that love can be blinding, and really, deeply wanting something to be good can shift you into a state of denial vis-a-vis that thing, and denial isn’t just a river in Africa. After a teenage love affair with The National’s <em>High Violet</em>, I really, really wanted to love <em>Trouble Will Find Me</em>; so much so that it took six months of listening until I realised I hated it. Love letters are first-personal, and so are told from within that rich framework of expectations and prejudices that is the inevitable by-product of being a living, breathing human.</p>
<p>Anyway, what is the point to all this? A justification, I guess, and a warning, that what follows is not, in any way, objective. What follows is first-personal. What follows is a love letter to a little bistro in Paris.</p>
<hr>
<p>Le Servan is the best restaurant in Paris, probably in France. Le Servan is one of the best restaurants in Europe. I’ve yet to find somewhere else that reminds me of why I love food, why I love wine, why I love the whole damn thing, every single time I visit.</p>
<p>We’ll begin with the chef. Tatiana Levha is one of the most talented chefs of her generation. She gives French cuisine what it so urgently needs – a kick up the arse (but a gentle, loving kick). Her cooking is rooted in the classical French tradition; she trained at L’Astrance and L’Arpège. It is technically gifted and sauce-forward. Pastry is well executed, subtle, and other good things. Strip back some of the innovation, squint a bit, tilt your head, and it reads like a page from the Escoffier playbook.</p>
<p>And while her menus march out some of the greatest hits – I’ve seen mussels, scallops Saint Jacques, steak tartare, poached eggs, and roast chicken on the menu (though unfortunately not on the same dish) – they’re also inventive, innovative. Most plates have a streak of Asian flavour, the echo of her childhood, in the rain in Manila, on the sweaty streets of Hong Kong. The mussels are served with chilli and Thai basil. Scallops Saint Jacques, carpaccioed, lie next to a soya cream (described by sommelier Victor as an ‘umami bomb’), chopped nori chucked on top. The steak tartare is as expected, but the egg yolk is confit, or creamed, or something, which drags out slightly more flavour and highlights slightly more texture. The next week – the menu changes on the reg – the steak tartare is drenched in lime and mixed with cashew and coriander. Poached eggs share the plate with leek, peanuts, chillis, ginger. Poulette, with crispy skin, appears frequently with cauliflower, browned and soaked in sauce, or maybe offset by pickled lemon.</p>
<p>But the innovation also isn’t really the point. Alone, and with various groups, I’ve visited loads of times, and each time the menu has changed, and each time the food is executed just as well, and each time I feel more welcomed, and more at home. The staff do more than put up with us – and I’m sure, when we’re three bottles in, ‘putting up’ is the right term – they genuinely seem to care for us, and for the food and wine that they’re serving. My vegan partner is cooked a bespoke vegetable plate, one that usually matches a main course in style. Flavour is judicious and homely and not trying very hard to impress you, which only makes it more impressive.</p>
<p>A few visits ago, I made some not-very-funny joke about how it’d be cool if a glass of wine arrived at our table the moment we sat down. At our next visit, the glass got to the table before we did. The front of house team, headed up by Katia, Tatiana’s sister, are thoughtful and fun and helpful and knowledgeable and completely unfussy, which, when set against the backdrop of Paris, is like a breath of fresh air after being stuck in a lift with an undiagnosed coeliac.</p>
<p>You might not have the same reaction. You might think the exposed brass bar too gauche, the tables too tightly squeezed in.  You might be peeved that it’s not open at weekends, and that it’s usually full the rest of the time, and that you can’t reserve online so have to awkwardly fumble through the conversation with your pre-GCSE French. You might think it overpriced, for what it is, really; a good-quality neighbourhood spot, but hardly Paul Bocuse, or The Fat Duck, or whatever. And you’d be right on every single count. I’ve sent friends whose expectations were set extremely high by my gushing, my saccharine soliloquies, and whose response was little more than ‘meh’.</p>
<p>But I don’t care. Because it’s <em>mine</em>. I love it. And it’s going to take a lot more than a few murmurs of dissent from friends to change that. This, I think, is the central paradox of criticism. Good criticism comes from a place of love. And love makes it very, very hard to be critical.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d/1548964626199-PB26V5GWP9BOS4KMX3PN/40645306_879564922251149_1278757062108556367_n.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1080" height="1080"><media:title type="plain">love letters</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>locavore</title><category>restaurants</category><dc:creator>Jamie Rumbelow</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2018 20:39:23 +0000</pubDate><link>https://littleleftover.com/blog/2018/9/17/locavore</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d:5a945a09652dea5235cfb463:5ba010598a922d03bdf4a97b</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Egghead is a vegan. She’s also thoughtful, so she’s a thoughtful vegan: her ideas undergo regular scrutiny, her opinions shift subtly to adjust for new evidence. She is the model of veganism, and discussing the ethical and environmental implications of food with her has helped clarify my own carnivorousness.</p>
<p>Food is important – sometimes <em>too</em> important – to me, and the kind of pleasure that I get through exploring and discussing it is, I think, an elevated one. It is a subject ripe for intellectualisation, ripe for thought and subtly. Food and its consumption flows throughout every layer of society down to an individual moment within the experience of an individual person; so it needs to be treated with importance and cultural recognition, in the sorts of aesthetic and ethical ways we critique art, fashion, thought. Which is an interesting complexity, because it’s also something so innate, so deeply pervasive, atavistic, that we can’t help but find ourselves responding immediately to what’s on our plate. Eating is, in so many cases, a sensual act, devoid of cognition. So where’s the line? When should a meal go from sustenance to sapience?</p>
<p>Egghead’s position begins and ends with suffering: she wishes (rightly so) to minimise it, and, at least a priori, judges that no amount of gastronomic pleasure can outweigh that suffering. That’s a bold claim, and something that I think she is somewhat flexible on. I’ve put to her a few times the standard point: whether an animal with a good, happy life, and a painless or near-painless death, has been treated well enough to justify its slaughter for consumption. By and large, she answers ‘no’.</p>
<p>L’Enclume is an interesting case study here, because nearly all of her arguments don’t apply. Damn-near everything served at the restaurant is grown or reared locally. Dairy cows are given gentle lives and wide pastures; sheep are reared and shorn with great care; all food is seasonal. Local fisherman are assessed for their ethical standards and the quality of the seafood they bring (two things which are so often connected.) For Egghead, the final sticking point (and the point where I believe her position finally fractures) is that the <em>taking of the life</em> is the problem, all else considered. But would you prefer to live a happy life and then be killed prematurely, rather than never having lived at all? And at what cost are we willing to obey an abstract injunction against the taking of a life, the use of a sentient being as an end, not a means?</p>
<p>It’s a sticky wicket for both Egghead and I. But L’Enclume makes me confident that, when done well, there is outsized value to be had by food grown locally and thoughtfully. Seasonality – so often a tired buzzword ejaculated over book covers – finds its spirit in this place, and it sings through everything put on the table.</p>
<p>You’re sat in an old blacksmith workshop, white overcast June light pouring in through a glass conservatory. Tables tastefully decorated. Little touches: an anvil, the restaurant’s logo, stamped on the steak knife; staff synchronised to bring the table’s food out at the same time (once even crossing half the room before quietly retreating when Egghead got up to go to the toilet); napkins carefully folded and replaced whenever necessary. Staff enthusiastic, helpful. Everything you should demand from two Michelin stars, but without the pomposity of more classic places.</p>
<p>A nine-course tasting menu, some of the best food I’ve ever eaten. A vegan option which stood out for its breadth of flavour and texture in a world where so often Egghead is consigned to eating a tomato-based stew. Three beetroot dishes begin, a tea made of its fermented juices, a leaf, carefully caramelised, a bulb smoked by and sat upon charred pines. Pork and eel for me, chickpea wafer for Egghead (something she still apparently dreams about – and I can see why.) Tartare, in both beef and semi-dehydrated heritage tomato form. Lamb and pollock and rhubarb and several clever desserts, all fresh, all light, all flavourful. All it needed is an Alvariño and the smell of asparagus piss and it would have been Spring incarnate.</p>
<p>Wonderful wine pairings and good coffee. A charming little town, Cartmel, though it’s a bit like Padstow – caught under the weight (and the brand) of its most famous son. A drunken kiss and an afternoon doze in a quiet hotel room. A near-perfect meal with a near-perfect companion. Eating locally, when done with the flair and thoughtfulness that Simon Rogan puts into his restaurants, will always prove its utility and importance to food, not just gastronomically, but ethically, environmentally, culturally too. To do things with flair and thoughtfulness: a good mantra, I think.</p>
<p>A good way to describe the work of Simon Rogan, for sure.</p>
<p>A good way to describe her, she who keeps me thinking.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d/1537216753466-JSKHF9GDRUE3YSTAO87G/IMG_1710.JPG?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1080" height="1080"><media:title type="plain">locavore</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>hype</title><category>restaurants</category><dc:creator>Jamie Rumbelow</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2018 18:10:08 +0000</pubDate><link>https://littleleftover.com/blog/2018/6/21/hype</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d:5a945a09652dea5235cfb463:5b2bea062b6a2848160255c5</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Living away from London, as I do now, makes engaging with its food scene a predominantly visual act. Dishes are mediated through carefully-filtered Instagram shots. Famous influencers influence, bloggers blog, and you sit aching on the sidelines. As you puff on your first cigarette of the day, Scottish sun beating on your brow, you watch story after story of meal after meal wishing there was something you could taste other than smoke.</p>
<p>Exciting new restaurants remain exciting, because you can’t get there. Hype is hyperactive, and ripples across the internet, and you fall for it every time. I’ve lived that <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BkHkpJoglLh/?taken-at=149786799064023">bloody turbot at Brat</a> a million times without ever having stepped into the place. I’ve experienced the collective sigh of bathos with the tasting menu at Hide, without tasting a single dish. I’ve perused the new bar menu at Lyle’s, scoured the Clove Club wine list for gems, and haven’t yet ordered from either.</p>
<p>But so much of it is hype. And a bit of distance makes you realise that. Deep in the throng, groaning under the weight of a  throbbing city, it’s hard to detach from what’s novel, what’s exciting, who’s wanted and why. For sure, social media exaggerates it. But when you’re unable to jump immediately from the new thing to the next, the gratification of novelty begins to wear off. You have time to pause, consider, regroup. Contemplate where you want to go and make the most – really make the most – of going, the next time you’re lucky enough to be hurtling toward King’s Cross on some Branson-branded train.</p>
<p>The Coach is a restaurant for those sorts of contemplative moments. Sure, it was hyped. But the hype fell away fast – is that happening faster nowadays? – and, besides, it lived up to it.</p>
<p>It’s not the sort of place, or cuisine, that sustains hype for very long. The place is decked out like a genuine, if somewhat upmarket, pub; stools, ales, a simple colour scheme. Nice wee beer garden in the back, conservatory, spacious upstairs dining room. Proper beer, Sunday lunch, and not a white linen tablecloth in sight. It’s a proper pub. Give it a few busy nights, euthanise the cleaning staff, and the place would fill up with spit and sawdust.</p>
<p>The food is magical, but really understated. It’s French bistro cooking, a little anglicised, a little modern, but somehow at the same time effortlessly classical. Rillettes, steak tartare. Provençal chicken, asparagus with hollandaise. Calf’s brains with capers in a black butter (texture a bit like paneer cheese, flavour a little like pork fat). According to people who know about these things, Henry Harris has imported a range of recipes in from his previous Brompton Road bistro Racine, such as the grilled rabbit in a mustard sauce with smoked bacon (which was delicious, by the way). He’s obviously been working at this for a while. But it’s done with such confidence, it almost feels laissez-faire. What comes out as simple on plate and palate belies a whole career learning, refining, and reinventing these sorts of dishes. It’s highly, highly accomplished.</p>
<p>The staff were quite simply <em>lovely</em>, both times I popped in, and the food consistently good. One of our waiters was almost giddy to tell us that Harris himself was in the kitchen on my debut visit. They seemed proud of what they were doing and what they were serving. Which they should be, because they and it are excellent.</p>
<p>And – ahh! How did I forget! Drop whatever you’re doing right now and get to London. The crème caramel. I’m not kidding. This is the sort of crème caramel to make your stoic father weep with the tears of angels. The sort to make you phone whoever writes the authoritative French <em>dictionnaire</em> and get them to redefine 'crème caramel' to only include this specific dish. Then phone the editor of the OED with the same request. It’s eggy and rich and nutty and creamy and it wobbles with glee and it sings with flavour and the fat renders on your tongue and, for one moment, life is suspended in immediate, truly immediate pleasure.</p>
<p>It’s excellent. Through and through. It’s consistent. It’s not overpriced, given I’ve had worse meals at places that charge three figures. It’s not overpriced to begin with. The wine list is simple but well balanced, the ales are kept well. It’s a pub’s pub, and a foodie’s restaurant, all in one subtle space.</p>
<p>The next time I’m <em>en route</em> to London, it’s going to be hard to go and try that bloody turbot, knowing that a little slice of Clerkenwell offers such a well executed experience. I only have to take a look at their Instagram account to be reminded: it really does live up to the hype.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d/1529604876654-W7JSDLW8A2MOAWAZPXFG/29096080_369700713532504_1694160196483416064_n.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1080" height="1080"><media:title type="plain">hype</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>doppio zero</title><category>cooking</category><dc:creator>Jamie Rumbelow</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2018 11:16:03 +0000</pubDate><link>https://littleleftover.com/blog/2018/3/28/doppio-zero</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d:5a945a09652dea5235cfb463:5abb790c70a6ad9323109e35</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Not too dry, or else it’ll tear and crumble. Not too damp; it’ll stick to the rollers. Eggs, but mostly yolk. Flour? Which flour? How much? Oil? Olive – obvs – if any. But perhaps none at all? Yeast, at least? Would salt be at fault? Rolling seems necessary. But does a machine? If not, how thin does it need to be? And should it be rolled against a certain wood, imparting a certain texture? Or is it enough to roll it oil-slick smooth, a perfect <em>sfoliga</em> of satin structure?</p>
<p>If I get it right, when will I know? And if I get it wrong, whom am I wronging?</p>
<hr>
<p>My first attempt – like most of my first attempts - was, well, crap. I’ve never been good at following recipes. My attitude to cooking has always been ‘art over science’, and any demands on me made by uncredentialed (and, gosh, <em>American</em>) food bloggers cut at the heart of why I thought I loved the activity. But this was just hubris, hypocrisy, an attitude borne from accidental splendour, lucky guesses, and no small amount of denial.</p>
<p>I knew I had to use flour and eggs, but that was it. I bought a cheap pasta machine at a local Italian deli, which came with a bag of 00 flour. The Italians grade their flour by extraction rate, how much of the bran and germ are extracted from the kernel during milling: ’00’ offers the whitest, purest, most <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Endosperm">endospermtacular</a> pastry experience. Pasta, it turns out, is variable, but forgiving: your flour can vary (roughly) along the lines of how textured you wish your pasta to be. Extruded pastas, your <em>penne</em> and <em>rigatoni</em>, your <em>macaroni</em> and <em>bucatini</em>, tend to demand something coarser, richer, stronger (usually semolina); the more typical fares of <em>pasta fresca</em>, <em>tagliatelle</em>, <em>parpadelle</em>, <em>linguini</em> and friends are happier when built up from a finer grain. But if authenticity isn’t a goal, then you can mix and match with gleeful abandon.</p>
<p>Of course, I knew none of this when I started. All I knew was that I’d heard the words ‘pasta’ and ‘semolina’ in the same sentence, uttered by someone, at some point. And so after a botched attempt to find semolina flour in the local Sainsbury’s, resignedly I grabbed the bag of Caputo “00” Rinforzata and cast exasperated eyes on the recipe for pasta dough printed on the paper bag. It read something like this:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>400g <em>Caputo “00” Rinforzata</em> flour</li>
<li>Four eggs</li>
<li>A little lukewarm water to loosen</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>So I gave it a go. I hate measuring anything, and, at any rate, don’t own scales. So I emptied roughly four fifths of the bag out onto my kitchen counter – which I had forgotten to clean; fuck – and made a well, a volcano’s chamber. That seemed sensible, sophisticated even, and buoyed by my cleverness I cracked on, emptying the eggs with a flourish into the centre of the well. Mixing the eggs properly took time; the well not deep my fork nicked the table with every downward flick. Slowly, however, I could incorporate more flour, and, like a teenage boy  dozing in the twilight hours, it started to stiffen.</p>
<p>Then? I knead. Not sure how to, really. Pushing it down, stretching it out, picking it up, collecting into a ball, repeat. Seemed to do the job.</p>
<p>But it was dry, and as I began to roll it out – stupidly straight through the machine, rather than first by hand – it collected more flour from dusted rollers, dusted countertop, and dried even further. By the time I was ready to start cutting it into strips of parpadelle, it had torn, crumbled, flaked under the pressure. It smelled of nothing, no gluten; it felt limp; it looked jagged and irregular. Beaten, spent. No grace, no finesse.</p>
<p>Still, don’t look back. Like Dylan in the movies. Back to the drawing board.</p>
<hr>
<p>That evening I gloated and whined in equal measure on the phone to Eli: I was happy to have even <em>bothered</em>; I was furious it wasn’t working. After a quick Q&amp;A to ascertain my technique, she suggested a glug of olive oil. This turned out to be the first important insight: oil adds an elasticity, a sponginess to the dough that eases kneading and forms a more robust pastry.</p>
<p>The second insight was to use mostly egg <em>yolks</em>, not the full eggs. Whites are almost entirely water, and while they like oil add some elasticity to the dough, they don’t impart much flavour; the more yolks and fewer whites one can use, the better. My third and fourth attempts were all-yolk, dough sat on the board glowing golden. When using an all-yolk mix, it’s important that you remember the oil; without the whites the dough becomes hard, crumbly, once more. It’s easy to overdose the dough at this point with gratuitous dustings of flour: don’t. Fight the urge, or all this work will be for nothing.</p>
<p>The recipe thus developed:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>400g “00” flour</li>
<li>One full egg</li>
<li>Six to eight egg yolks</li>
<li>A splash of olive oil (not much more than a tablespoon)</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>The water is superfluous to requirements. If it looks like it needs loosening earlier on, add another egg yolk; if it needs loosening later, a little oil. If you must, a splash of water can do, but most of the hydration will come from the egg white, and you should need to add little else.</p>
<p>(A side note: the total amount of hydration required depends on precisely what you need to do. Filled pastas like <em>tortelli</em> need an impossibly thin pasta – it should be translucent – and so require more water content to prevent them from tearing. Anything thicker and the water will render the pasta bland, so experiment with it.)</p>
<p>Eventually, after a good pounding, this dough came out beautifully. The third insight: keep kneading until you smell the gluten. It puts up a fight, but if you continue to gently massage the dough, for ten or so minutes, it will capitulate and a rich, deep smell reminiscent of supermarket bakeries will be your reward. Once this has happened, the pastry will be pliable and, most importantly, will release the starch to the surface when cooked. Starchy pasta water is the secreto numero uno to great pasta dishes: it gives sauces their glossy texture; it binds the sauce to the noodles; it provides the drone note in the Gregorian chant that is the meal. It underlies everything, and whatever you can do at the dough stage to encourage it is time spent well.</p>
<hr>
<p>I’m going on a bit now, so I’ll conclude this quickly. After ten or so iterations, the details of which I won’t belabour any further, I have arrived at what I <em>think</em> is the best pasta dough I’m capable of making. I hope to study pasta properly in Italy at some point, and when I do I’m expecting to lose this confidence: it is a subtle art, and one of deep history and ethical consequence. But, for now, I’m happy.</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>300g “00” flour</li>
<li>100g semolina flour</li>
<li>One full egg</li>
<li>Six to eight egg yolks</li>
<li>A splash of olive oil (not much more than a tablespoon)</li>
<li>A pinch of salt</li>
</ul>
<p>Mix the flour in a bowl, then empty onto a clean(!) work surface. Create a well, and fill it with the eggs. With a fork lightly whisk the eggs until mixed together. Then add the oil and salt, and whisk again. Begin to incorporate flour in from the edges of the well until the fork becomes an irrelevance.</p>
<p>Get your hands dirty, knead, push, stretch. After ten minutes, the dough will give up the gluten. Then? You roll. Roll the pasta out with a rolling pin (or an empty wine bottle; student life). Feed it through the machine, twice or thrice on each setting, gradually getting thinner. I’m lazy so often skip a few; that’s fine. Cut however your heart sings to you, whatever the sauce demands, and cook in water salted to resemble the sea for a minute or two. Don’t worry too much about <em>al dente</em>; pasta fresca usually side-steps it. Save the salty, starchy cooking water to bind your pasta to the sauce. Mix well. Serve.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Buon appetito.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d/1522235756168-RM41NRX51BZEK7QK1WYC/28753262_2160489137532006_2339547064989384704_n.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1080" height="1080"><media:title type="plain">doppio zero</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>"moments"</title><category>travel</category><dc:creator>Jamie Rumbelow</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2018 07:54:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://littleleftover.com/blog/2018/2/20/moments</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d:5a945a09652dea5235cfb463:5a950ebd24a694ce120d11de</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>You’ll begin with a <em>pastel de nata</em>, I’m sure of that. It all begins and ends with pastéis, and rightly so: the first bite, teeth tearing through puffed-up folds of pastry, the crunch and burst and splatter of custard. I felt that I was witnessing, experiencing, eating something with great history. Before I went to Lisbon, I was told of little else. Phil Rosenthal’s annoying, upbeat, para-Bourdain travel show; Tony himself, some late episode of <em>No Reservations</em>; my mother, of course; a friend with some expat experience; a Portuguese colleague; a teller in the bank; an assorted army of Facebook connections. Nobody could hear the words ‘Lisbon’ or ‘Portugal’ without falling into a state of rapturous gushing, fawning for city and pastel alike. It boded very well.</p>
<p>I came to realise quite quickly that the pastel de nata was more than a gastronomic feat; it was a triumph of marketing. Somebody, somewhere, has managed to push it into the global consciousness in such an effective way, the city – Lisboeta life – seems inseparable from it. It’s like the Italian’s <em>caffè al banco</em> (a short-sharp-shock of espresso, taken leaning against a bar). You slam your euro down, grumble about something to the barista, break into the fine film formed on the surface of the custard, wipe flecks of pastry from your face. Two bites, maybe three. Sluice a shot of espresso down your throat like soap suds in a sink. Get on with your day. It’s ritualised, and like all new rituals, it gets under your skin much quicker than you’d expect.</p>
<p>So you start with pastéis. You’ll flock to the westerly Belém – an old store sat in a beautiful garden adjacent to a stunning gothic church, a nod to pastel’s humble monastic pedigree – but you’ll be wrong, because the bar is crowded and touristic and full of Germans and really quite dirty and the service was bad and the waiter was miserable and so was the pastel. Stick to town: Manteigaria in the Mercardo Ribeira is a much better bet, or, for an even more authentic experience, their shop further uptown on the Rua do Loreto.</p>
<p>One pastel isn’t enough, of course, and you’ve got a lot of walking to do. So while you’re in the Mercardo you flit around the stalls, a Portuguese <a href="www.mercatometropolitano.co.uk">Mercato Metropolitano</a>, at once both food hall and safe space. Stuff your face with something – the Manteigaria Silva stall will do for now: cheese and various cured bits of pig and there’s enough Duoro wine to get you more than comfortably drunk for a morning’s rambling.</p>
<p>Lunch time swings round much quicker than you expect, but so does your hunger, so you don’t mind. A steep flight of steps leads up from Calçada Ferrigal to a small, dusty side road, and on to a cold, anonymous entrance hall, and up another flight, this time carpeted, and through a door which the wind slams shut behind you. You struggle with your lousy Portuguese to befriend the nun behind the counter. She looks confused, then resigned, then dumps you in the canteen adjacent. You’re led by your bemused ex-girlfriend to the terrace where Lisbon’s terracotta rooftops meet the sky meets the hills meet the Tagus all around you. Squid and rice is shovelled onto your plate, and the sun bursts through the clouds. Pigeons throw themselves at you (you always had a way with birds) and the city hums beneath your feet.</p>
<p>The hunger hits again around 3pm, and dinner’s not booked until eight, so you’ll need something to take the edge off. The sun’s hidden away again – it’s only February – so you’ll dive over to <em>Sol e Pesca</em> (insert joke about Michael Fish). Tinned sardines will do it, you’re sure of that. Let the oil soak onto the bread, order a <em>garrafa</em> of alvarinho. Hundreds of varieties to choose from, most cheap, all beautifully packaged. Before you know it you’re sprinting up to the castle, fortified by fish. The sun begins to set around seven so you make your way back down, through the town, past the endless queues of people outside the tram 28. When will they learn?</p>
<p>All dolled-up in shirts and elegant dresses you march onward to Cantinho do Avillez, a last minute suggestion, the comparatively laid-back relaxed bistro affair from José Avillez, sister restaurant to tomorrow’s Belcanto. En route you stop for a ginjinha – ask for it with ice (<em>com xielo</em>, I think) – and, remarkably, the booze tips you over the edge and straight back into hunger. Thank God you’re hungry, because you’re in for a treat. Tuna tartare lightly dressed with sesame but left singing. That’s something I can’t stress enough: the whole point of Lisboeta food is <em>produce produce produce</em>, and, well, fuck me. Tuna tartare. It’s simple, so simple, but it’s a learned simplicity. And <em>such</em> an accomplished one. Alentejo black pork, sat atop of farofa and some black beans that my friend’s fiancé would describe as nothing short of cosmic. Another bottle of alvarinho, a really good one this time. A hazelnut whip - grown-up Nutella in a bowl – a glass of Madeira. A totally respectable €130 bill: food this good, wine this good, for two people, with liqueurs, service included.</p>
<p>Then careering over the road to Topo, hidden in an ugly commercial centre, elevator doors opening to a hit of cold air, cardamom, tequila, cigarettes. Rooftop bar pulsing with music. Shitfaced in the cool Portuguese night. And that’s day one.</p>
<hr>
<p>You’ve eaten too much. Hah! Do some walking, because you’re going to Belcanto this evening and you’ll need the stamina. One of the more appealing recommendations from Rosenthal’s awkwardly chirpy Netflix debut is <em>Ponto Final</em>, and it’s a treck, but the view is worth it. Pleasant ferry ride across, though it’s foggy, and the ferry is enclosed, so the journey isn’t quite as jaw-dropping as the Star Ferry in Hong Kong, say, or the view of Manhattan glittering at night from the Staten Island approach. Once you’re across the estuary, you walk past boathouses and old, grizzled fisherman, until the path narrows, the sea spraying against the concrete, and you reach a tiny, remote, restaurant. Tables and chairs stick out into the sea – look ma, no railings! – and as the fog starts to lift, the contours of Lisbon start to reveal themselves across the bay. Walk on further, up an elevator, round some dusty streets, and you’ll find Jesus (always in the last place you look, eh?)</p>
<p>In homage to Rio, Salazar and the Church (which, for much of the former’s rule, were much the same thing) decided to install a towering statue of our great saviour in the wee town of Almada. Choral music drifts out of the speaker system, an inexplicable smell of barbecued pork, a phenomenal view. It’s all of five euros to get to the top, and worth every penny. But it’s a stark  and constant reminder of a Lisbon that hasn’t forgotten its past, and as he leers over the city, over drinks and meals and exams and interviews, over people fucking and crying and fighting, over the grinding minutiae of life, you can’t help but feel – like with so much religion – it’s all a little bit voyeuristic, excessively paternal, maybe even Orwellian. Exactly the kind of life that the Portuguese collectively remember and collectively wish to forget.</p>
<p>No time for <em>saudade</em>, though, when there’s food to eat. José’s relaxed, informal affair is morphed a few streets over into the indelibly classy Belcanto (holder of Portugal’s only two-michelin stars). A fourteen-course (what the waiter referred to as “moments”, shudder) tasting menu, radical, traditional, incrementally experimental all at once. An ‘elderflowertini’ with frozen olives, shotted as sorbet; “moments” (shudder) two through six delivered together next: chickpea and cod stones; lobster claw with yuzu mayonnaise; Azores tuna tartare; something forgettable and chestnutted; pork; five delicious amuse-bouches all lined up side by side. After the first six “moments” (shudder), the pace begins to slow a little: ceviche; a brief introduction to a lobster who is whisked away and promptly despatched; wonderfully fresh shrimp; subtly poached egg yolk with caviar; sea bass with smoked avocado; the lobster we met earlier, returned to the table (looking much less energetic); calamari and risotto; pork. It is now two hours on, and each of the nine wines on the pairing list (and the champagne you started with) have blended into one and sunk into your stomach, mingling with the seafood. A blur of birthday cake, cheese, chocolate, strawberry and lychee, coffee petit fours. You stumble up the street, unsure where you’re going, but convinced that the brain-GPS will kick in and direct you subconsciously. You were right; you fall into bed.</p>
<p>And that’s day two.</p>
<hr>
<p>How could I talk about Lisbon without mentioning <em>Cerverjaria Ramiro</em>? The place is legendary for its seafood, and you understand why. It’s packed, queues stretching out onto the street from the moment you arrive to the moment you leave. It’s also quite expensive, but the freshness of the seafood, portion sizes, and general chaos of the dining room is worth the investment. I’m starting to bore myself now, so I won’t provide a full itinerary of the meal, but make sure you try the <em>percebes</em> (goose barnacles; little wrinkled phallic ingrowths surrounded by a protective almost cow-skin, rough, leathery casing; I’m not really selling it, am I?); crab (bigger than your head); tiger prawns (bigger than the crab); and make sure you leave room for dessert, which, confusingly, is a <em>prego</em>, a steak and mustard sandwich.</p>
<p>Cross the street: behind a large door, bouncer, all very <a href="http://www.chinatownecc.com/">ECC-on-Gerrard-St</a>, all very clandestine, all rather unwelcoming, lies Casa Independente. It’s an old palazzo of sorts, now bar-cum-art-project, a series of strange, inviting, Kubrickesque rooms painted pastel-coloured, an outside courtyard where drinks are being shaken and everybody – literally everybody – is cry-myself-to-sleep beautiful.</p>
<p>You can drink wine and talk and smoke cigarettes here for hours. You can argue and debate and sip on cocktails, tiredness creeping over you like a raincloud, full of food, full of happiness and nostalgia. In London, the basic currency is busyness; in Lisbon, it is nostalgia. You’ll see the sad history of the place littered around, hidden from sight but always lurking, weighing down. You’ll see the young brush shoulders with the old, edging their way in, an energy and vibrance poised in the wings, ready to thrust this tired pace to one side. You can drink wine and ponder all of this, the manifest complexities and contradictions, that confused, brief glimpse into a world so familiar yet different. It’s the reason you travel at all.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d/1519718406919-AMM6JTAS13F9KAVX2WE9/IMG_0936.JPG?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1500"><media:title type="plain">"moments"</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>pictures of you</title><category>wine</category><dc:creator>Jamie Rumbelow</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 10:54:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://littleleftover.com/blog/2018/2/27/not-what-you-know</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d:5a945a09652dea5235cfb463:5a951c82e4966b1aa55f4911</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Pictured is a bottle of Chateau Musar 2006. <a href="https://chateaumusar.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/1.-Chateau-Musar-Red-2006-tasting-notes.pdf">Its tasting notes</a> promise us smells of “confected cherry, blackcurrant and cranberries” with just a “hint of liquorice”. On the palate, we’re told to look out for “brambly and hedgerow fruits”, “blueberries”, “cherries”, “excellent acidity” and “fine tannins”.</p>
<p>I’m not really sure what that means. How does one confect a cherry? And how does its smell differ from an unconfected one? How much liquorice constitutes a hint; how much a smack in the face? I think I have some idea – I’ve drank my fair share of Musar – but every time I drink a glass my answers to these questions change, my senses altered, my powers of description irrevocably morphed into something new.</p>
<p>See, the trouble is, I wouldn’t describe Musar in those words. At all. Not even close. My little tasting book – I’ve promised Oskar, my wine father, to keep detailed notes on whatever I try – records my first ever bottle:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Wood (oak?), the inside of a tobacco pouch (David’s car?), weird cabbage thing. Nice tannins, blackberry, lamb?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Most of my notes are like that. I didn’t know what I was writing then. I still don’t know. I just did what I was told: take your immediate, arresting, sensory reaction to the wine and write down whatever you think fits.</p>
<p>Oskar’s response to a red Burgundy once (so good I recorded it):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Strawberries crushed on the back of a sweaty horse</p>
</blockquote>
<p>These pictures are evocative. David’s car is evocative for me – David smokes a pipe – just as your childhood laundry detergent might be evocative for you, or the smell of the metal on the slide in the park, or the slightly sickly smell of nearly-burning milk and definitely-burning coffee that hits you when you open the door to a Starbucks, or the rubbish bin in the kitchen just after Mum had been cooking, or the taste of a hot chocolate with whipped cream, or the texture of the marshmallows you put in it. These images are evocative to me, just like an image of a hot, clammy horse mixing with the pulp of summer fruits was evocative for Oskar. Each vignette is a palimpsest of an earlier memory, a trace of sense abstracted and categorised, filed under some label or other, hidden away to be relived, changed, at some point in the future.</p>
<p>My life is different now. I drink different drinks, eat different food, use different laundry detergent. I’ve been introduced to ingredients I never knew existed, found a vocabulary to describe tastes I never knew I needed. Tomatoes taste different to me now after spending time in Italy; vanilla, saltwater, sesame all have a different importance to me <a href="https://littleleftover.com/blog/2018/2/20/moments">after visiting Lisbon</a>.</p>
<p>The memories we hold onto are relived through the irreducibly first-personal, the filter of the present. It’s why you look back on being wronged by a friend first indignantly, then wistfully, then with the resigned humour that only comes with age and distance. Its effects are most profound on the olfactory and gustatory senses, because all you really have is some vocabulary and some little, ineffable whisper of a subjective experience. So each word is loaded with every time, phrase, feeling, past and present, that you’ve attached to it.</p>
<p>We can drink a bottle of Musar 2006 together, have exactly the same experience, and yet smell something completely different. And yes, if we want to communicate these differences with each other, we must converge on the similarities and work our way outward. We must share a vocabulary, beginning with David’s car and working our way toward smouldering beech with a hint of liquorice, our memories entwining and dancing with our experiences, THAT wine THEN compared to THIS wine now, inescapably bound to our childhoods, forced to see novelty as evolution rather than revolution, flavours, smells, our feelings, borne back ceaselessly into the past.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d/1519721629406-IRZ5PMBSV8VXLN9SZI69/IMG_0583.JPG?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1500"><media:title type="plain">pictures of you</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>pidgin / magpie</title><category>restaurants</category><dc:creator>Jamie Rumbelow</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 11:22:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://littleleftover.com/blog/2018/2/27/pidgin-magpie</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d:5a945a09652dea5235cfb463:5a95199771c10b3c2cd9752a</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>James Ramsden and Sam Herlihy are very funny men. Piss-yourself-on-the-tube funny. It’s impossible to listen to an episode of their <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/gb/podcast/the-kitchen-is-on-fire/id916786736?mt=2"><em>The Kitchen Is On Fire</em></a> podcast without laughing. They spend an hour or so each week talking bollocks, occasionally related to food, often not. They produce their own adverts a million miles away from the standard <em>Sponsored by Squarespace</em>: the past few episodes include Tom Hardy’s Bane and the computer voice from Radiohead’s <em>Fitter, Happier</em>, both flogging wine for a sponsor. And when they do get around to discussing food, they do it with a confidence and a sense of ownership that betrays the what I’m sure is tens of thousands of hours they’ve collectively spent thinking, writing and talking about food.</p>
<p>In preparation for this post, I went back and listened to their very first episode – I started following around ep.110 – and was struck by a conversation about five minutes in. They’re sat there, a couple of awkward giggles, fumbling a little, finding their voices; all very first-podcast stuff. James asks Sam why they’re doing it: “For me, a lot of the talk about food - particularly in this country - is bound by tradition; and when it’s not, the English version of food not bound by tradition tends to be...”, he pauses, searching for ‘Reggae-Reggae Sauce’, “it doesn’t all have to be the same six or seven people talking about the same six or seven dishes over and over again”.</p>
<p>This was true in 2014. It’s changing now. The rise of publications like <a href="https://london.eater.com">Eater</a> and <a href="https://www.foodism.co.uk">Foodism</a> offer avenues for people to discover new, varied, different food. Food TV is changing: David Chang’s <em>Ugly Delicious</em> feels a bit like a Tarantino movie; Aziz Ansari’s <em>sfoligno</em> storyline in <em>Master of None</em>; even <em>Chef’s Table</em> is resetting the focus onto food as a central component of our shared experience, rather than the tired old straight-to-camera itinerary in sterilised studios.</p>
<p>Restaurants are changing, too. Honest Burger tells a telling story. Food trucks turn to pop-ups turn to crystallised moments in the restaurant zeitgeist. And so, fan of the show, how excited I was to discover that not only have James and Sam started a restaurant, their first foray had won a Michelin star; and, off the back of the success of the first, they’d started a second.</p>
<hr>
<p>James and Sam have set themselves the unenviable task of rewriting the menu, in its entirety, every week. Some fifty pounds buys you a four-course set menu. According to <a href="http://www.pidginlondon.com/menu">its website</a>, in over two years, they have yet to repeat a single dish. When the menu changes so frequently, it’s difficult to judge it on the success of any given plate of food. It lives and dies with the experience you have: the meal in its soaring, all-encompassing totality. As <a href="http://www.egoscriptor.space/home/2016/10/25/post-pidgin">George Reynolds wrote</a>, “it is the other stuff – the stuff that writers usually pick up on only when a restaurant gets it wrong – that remains.” The other stuff was executed mostly well. The food was executed mostly well. It was a perfectly pleasant, clever meal.</p>
<p>We began with what was a solid, crisped version of French onion soup. Egg slow cooked, green onion sauce, onion tapioca. If only there’d been some gratinéed Gruyère. Onion was followed by Mackerel. Mackerel was followed by beef. Beef was followed by a sourdough ice cream – fucking <em>delightful</em> – served with a Jurançon and a brownie with green pepper mousse.</p>
<p>But while the meal sang, it also missed its top C; a menu that changes every week, I think, will rarely hit the the higher notes. There’s still the Asian influence of its founding chef, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_Haigh">Elizabeth Haigh</a> (mackerel cured with soy and miso), but it feels less confident than it once seemed. I’m talking out of my arse, of course – I’ve only visited once – but <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2015/oct/23/pidgin-london-e8-restaurant-review-marina-oloughlin">other</a> <a href="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/food-and-drink/restaurants/pidgin-london-review/">reviews</a> have given me vicarious second opinions. What could have thrilled, sent shivers down spines, only lightly grazed the thigh.</p>
<p>It was quite a lovely evening (I think my friend Jess was less impressed; but it may just have been my company). But the little things that pulled it down were, I think, most of its on-paper charm. The beef dish was perfectly cooked, but dull. It needed heat: mustard, I suggested; horseradish, Jess countered; as usual, she was right. It was the sort of minor problem that would have been figured out, corrected, and laughed about, had the dish been on the menu for longer than six days. The décor was lovely: it’s a tiny little shopfront on a small Hackney residential street; the closest thing to Honey and Co that I’ve found outside of Honey and Co. The service was perfectly good, but it was spoilt when our waiter was very smarmy when we prevaricated over some wine. He'd been busy – it's a small place – and duly apologised later in the night, but fuck, he was rude.</p>
<hr>
<p>After our meal at Pidgin, I spent a week or two trying to figure out what I think had gone wrong. Nothing was <em>that</em> obvious (moody service notwithstanding), but something was a little off anyway, and I wanted to work out why.</p>
<p>So I went to Magpie, the duo’s second foray. And it hit me. Magpie felt cared for. It was new, fresh, exciting. It was the lover to Pidgin’s long-term spouse. Whereas Pidgin had set into its ways, Magpie had only just left the nest, featherless and eager to explore.</p>
<p>Make sure you have the whipped lardo bruschetta, and the cumin-baked nuts. I could have feasted on the starters alone, but it was the little meal that could, and it kept on giving. I’d arrived early, so sat at the bar and had a drink or two; a couple of starters set me up well, and, impressed by the nuts as I was, one of the chefs came out and gave me the recipe. Those touches, that care, that thought, set it miles apart from most restaurants – I hadn’t even had the meal by this point – and set it miles apart from Pidgin. If it’s the other stuff that we should focus on, then Magpie scored where Pidgin missed. So much great wine on tap, little trolleys of little plates circulating around its Heddon Street dining hall, staff that laughed and cared. An experience that sang, and hit the top C. </p>
<p>But it wasn’t just the other stuff. The food was superlative. Beef tartare with taleggio and egg yolk; burrata; celeriac <em>’cacio e pepe’</em>; pork collar with endive; cod with pickled pak choi. Everything was flawless. It was a lovely, lovely, lovely meal. I’m getting drunk and happy just thinking about it. Coffee and mezcal ice cream rounded it all off. Colour and flavour and smell and the bustle of the restaurant; it stuck to my senses.</p>
<hr>
<p>We’re now in the Open Era of food, and I couldn’t be happier. New people – enthusiastic amateurs – are freer and fitter and happier to experiment, to create, than ever before. The growing Ramsden/Herlihy empire is a wonderful expression of that freedom. They and many others are giving life to a whole new way of thinking and experiencing food, something I’m hoping to explore a more on this blog, something I’m thrilled to be able to witness. But exerting energy is tiring, and it takes the sort of stamina (only acquirable through experience) to maintain it. When the dust settles, the successful restaurateurs will be the ones that manage to slog through the slow times, the recessions, the fads and waves, losing stars, gaining new ones. No matter how fresh and new a place is, it’s only as good as the last plate of food it served. It's something takes a commitment gained through <em>work</em>, nothing else, and so, paradoxically, something gained through time and maturity. Pidgin was born from a supper club; Magpie was born from a restaurant. That's what makes the difference.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d/1519721261798-ENMV2F0WECMMCD9VPIQW/IMG_1783.JPG?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="2000"><media:title type="plain">pidgin / magpie</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>horses as courses</title><category>travel</category><dc:creator>Jamie Rumbelow</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2018 08:49:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://littleleftover.com/blog/2018/2/27/horses-as-courses</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d:5a945a09652dea5235cfb463:5a951b4171c10b3c2cd9a3ec</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>The notion of ‘New Nordic’ has always been an unsatisfying one. Like ‘Modern European’, it acts as a grab-bag for whatever happens not to fit elsewhere, a lazy catch-all label thrown onto meals far away from one another on the tree of family resemblences; unlike ‘Modern European’, it seems imbibed with stereotypes, fit for words like ‘rugged’, ‘wild’, ‘hardy’, ‘crude’ and ‘homely’, an oh-so-<em>hygge</em> nod to something forged in a cable-nit sweater, facing the warmth of a fire, set against a cold, dark world so different to ours. It seems a by-word for either ‘comfortable’, ‘unrefined’, or both.</p>
<p>It’s bollocks, of course. One need only watch the <em>Fäviken</em> episode of <em>Chef’s Table</em>, read Nilsson’s <em>Nordic Cookbook</em>, talk to anybody at any time about any aspect of <em>Noma</em>, to see that the New Nordic movement is capable of such sophistication and brilliance you wonder why you’ve not experienced more of it. It is no more beholden to its stereotypes than Italian cooking is beholden to moustachioed chefs serving spag bol. But still, Nordic countries <em>do</em> share a common history, and so there <em>is</em> some common core to their cooking, even if one much more complex and vital than a can of Ikea meatballs and a shot of akvavit will teach you.</p>
<p>The trouble is, everywhere I looked in Iceland, all I found were the stereotypes. Did the New Nordic movement pass it by? It can’t have done, but I saw so little of it.</p>
<hr>
<p>Geographically, Iceland is utterly, completely, overwhelmingly unique. Its sparse landscape, jagged rock branching out of volcanic substrate. The pungency, acridity of the sulfur in the water supply. The clarity and crushing coldness of the air. The licks of Aurora in the shadowed sky.</p>
<p>Just as the location feels rugged and wild, its food feels hardy and crude. The ingredients lend themselves to a sparse, socialist, utilitarian style of cooking. The twenty-hour-long nights drag on throughout winter, demanding that food be artificially preserved. Salted cod, cured salmon, fermented shark. Chewy puffin and tough, flavourless pony, both smoked to a tasteless oblivion. Pickled herring, of course; seaweed and prawns and rye bread. Brennivín, a type of akvavit; beer.</p>
<p>Sure, when in Rome, and we ate it all happily, if sometimes a little warily. Exhaust-pipe horse was one thing, but the herring was delicious, and rye is the true underdog of the Anglophone bread tradition, so it was great to find a ready supply. My bemused ex-girlfriend tucked into a Reindeer burger with sheer glee.</p>
<p>But from our all-too-brief, all-too-novice, all-to-shallow flirtation with Icelandic cuisine, it felt so… homogenous? It was regional, acquired, ruthlessly Icelandic eating, because there was little else it could have been. When the winter lasts eight months and little can grow, what are your options? When you’re far enough away from other countries to make pre-industrial trading an expensive dream, what else is going to happen?</p>
<p>And when centuries of food culture are left to ferment, like a shark, in cold warehouses and stark tundras, then tastes become adapted to those inevitable conditions. Tastes sit in a cultural marketplace, driven by both demand and supply: when supplies are short, they adapt from necessity; when abundant, they are already entrenched, so demand what they know. Parents pass down recipes to children, friends cook for other friends, restaurants feel compelled to cater to customers. It becomes a virtuous, or, more likely, vicious, circle. This is why, amongst other reasons, immigration is so important.</p>
<p>Next time I go, I’ll make sure I coincide with the <a href="http://www.foodandfun.is/">Food and Fun festival</a>, which seems to be shaking things up in a slow, defrosting kind of way. It was a beautiful place, and, to an extent greater than anywhere else I’ve ever visited, its culture was shaped by its geography. It was the first time I realised how vulnerable food can be to climate, which, now I think of it, is pretty fucking obvious.</p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d/1519721579835-Y8RC3YWAK2G3IL1WEKW9/IMG_0639.JPG?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1500" height="1125"><media:title type="plain">horses as courses</media:title></media:content></item><item><title>little things</title><category>restaurants</category><dc:creator>Jamie Rumbelow</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 19:31:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://littleleftover.com/blog/2017/11/24/little-things</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d:5a945a09652dea5235cfb463:5a9460a5e4966b828ccfd900</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>Tasting menus are a big risk for both diner and chef. When they’re good, they’re really good. No messing around. No vacillating between confit this or slow-roasted that. Just exceptional produce, exceptionally cooked. Choices made for you. Plenty of pretension, but adequately judged. No cognitive overload, no compromises. Wine paired, food served. The arc of the meal clearly defined.</p>
<p>But with each course, each time the – gastronomy? genre? narrative? – dives and twists and turns, each moment the waiters glide up to and away from the table, each percussive pop of a cork, each innocuous clink of cutlery against crockery, each splash of <em>jus</em> against shirt or tablecloth, the chances of something going wrong increase. And sometimes, just sometimes, that’s what happens. When they’re good, they’re really good. But when they’re not? You might leave full, you might leave drunk, but you might leave unsatisfied.</p>
<p>I wonder if I’d have enjoyed The Peat Inn more had I dined à la carte. I had high hopes, I really did. My local wine-merchant, Peter, recommended it very highly. The Michelin guide, Great British Chefs, Jay Rayner, all waxing lyrical. And after three months in St Andrews, three months of canteen food, burgers, student curry deals, I had been dreaming of fine dining: of reductions and jellies and things browned with blowtorches and other things quenelled and perhaps, if I was lucky, something made with liquid nitrogen, or at least something equally silly. I had high hopes.</p>
<p>Lots of game, Peter promised. And lots of game I was delivered: partridge, breast and leg, smoked, cut across with a maple vinegar and chestnut sauce. Potato purée, parsnips, glazed salsify. Mountain hare melting into an odd but subtly lovely mix of celeriac and truffle (branded as ‘risotto’, which got my hopes up even more). It was fucking delicious (even if the risotto wasn’t risotto at all and I threw a minor tantrum in front of my bemused ex-girlfriend).</p>
<p>Local fish, Peter promised. And local fish I was delivered: sea trout, Orkney langoustines, beetroot and horseradish velouté. Butch, proper, Scottish. Very Scottish. Scallop tartare, calamari. Little flakes of raddish and staccato black sesame.</p>
<p>There is so much to recommend the place. The decor, at once rococo and clean. The service, pandering and charming in just the right quantities. Staff knowledgeable and patient, informed and informing, entertaining and dedicated. Chef-Patron Geoffrey Smeddle is clearly a very talented guy with an enthusiasm for restaurants that reaches far beyond the kitchen.</p>
<p>But something didn’t quite click. And I promise I’m not blind to my privilege – it was a fantastic meal by anybody’s standards, and I feel lucky to have experienced it. But I want to be clear-headed about this, and something – <em>something</em> – felt the tiniest bit off.</p>
<p>The scallop tartare wasn’t fresh enough. It was a little bit too fishy, a little bit too weather-worn, a little bit too flaccid. The langoustines needed cleaning, so my pinot was more grit than gris. The cheese course was a clusterfuck and I don’t want to talk about it. The feuilleté was lovely, but basically a bit boring. Geoffrey had Smeddled too much with the plum sorbet; it ached with confusion. The more expensive ‘vintage’ wine pairing didn’t really justify the extra 40 quid; all the thought had gone into the (somewhat confusingly-titled) ‘classic’ pairing – which, in the end, didn't always pair.</p>
<p>When you’re committing to six or more courses – six courses not chosen by you, not even designed on your behalf, but instead chosen at Smeddle’s prerogative, an expression of his world-view – you’re investing in the whole meal. The whole experience. Whether you think they do or not, the failures of one course spill over into the next; a poor dessert leaves a taste in your mouth that colours your memories of the starter, a poorly chosen wine dampens the success of the perfect pairing the course before. It’s not terminal – it rarely is – but it takes away from that pure, raw, atavistic joy that accompanies an exceptional meal.</p>
<p>If you dine à la carte, the chef is cooking for you. When you opt for a tasting menu, he's cooking for <em>him</em> – so you put yourself at his mercy. You have trusted his judgement. And sometimes – rarely, but sometimes – that judgement fails you.</p>
<p>So perhaps if I’d had fewer courses, been more deliberate, exposed myself to less risk, I would have been more upbeat about the whole thing. All things considered, it was a good meal. I left full, I left drunk. But I left a little unsatisfied.</p>
<p><em>Image thanks to Great British Chefs.</em></p>]]></description><media:content type="image/jpeg" url="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5a943e0245776ed6ca08511d/1519674377458-46GOBWBSR1PPYJ4HZLL1/peatinn.jpg?format=1500w" medium="image" isDefault="true" width="1426" height="951"><media:title type="plain">little things</media:title></media:content></item></channel></rss>